Finding Aid for Arnold Gingrich Papers 1932-1975
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Speeches/Symposia
  - Dated Speeches
    - 1971
      - Bridgeport Area Chamber of Commerce and Bridgeport Commission on the Arts September 27, 1971 (Box 10)
        [10-25]
      - Twentieth Century Club, Cleveland, Ohio November 24, 1971 (Box 10)
        [10-26]
    - 1972
      - Council for the Arts in Westchester at Ciba-Geigys Corp. Ardsley, New York June 1, 1972 (Box 10)
        [10-27]
      - American Symphony Orchestra League Conference, Cincinnati, Ohio June 16, 1972 (Box 10)
        [10-28]
      - "Museums and Money: Separate Worlds?" Phoenix (Ariz.) Art Museum October 26, 1972 (Box 10)
        [10-29]
    - 1973
      - Lakefront Festival of Arts, Milwaukee, Wis. January 23, 1973 (Box 10)
        [10-30]
      - First Annual Corporate Social Responsibility Advertising Award speech; Department of Journalism talk, University of Michigan September 1973 (Box 10)
        [10-31]
    - 1974
      - ABC Encore Awards Luncheon, New York City November 20, 1974 (Box 10)
        [10-32]
    - 1975
      - undated (Box 10)
        [10-33]
      - Philadelphia Orchestra's Women's Committee Membership Campaign March 6, 1975 (Box 10)
        [10-34]
      - Northeast Trout Forum March 22, 1975 (Box 10)
        [10-35]
      - Eastern Council Conclave May 30, 1975 (Box 10)
        [10-36]
      - Miscellaneous speech material, 4 folders (Box 10)
        [10-37, etc. 10-40]
  - Symposia
    - Esquire Magazine Symposium, October 9-10, 1958 "The Role of the Writer in America" (Box 10)
      [10-41]
    - Esquire Magazine Symposium, October 20-21, 1960:, "Writing in America Today" (Box 10)
      [10-42]
    - Esquire Magazine Symposium, April 19-20, 1963 "The Pursuit of Excellence in the Creative Arts", 3 folders (Box 10)
      [10-43, etc.-10-45]
    - Esquire Magazine Symposium, April 29, 1964 "The State of Theatre", 2 folders (Box 10)
      [10-46; 10-47]
    - Esquire Magazine Symposium, April 5-6, 1965 Chapel Hill, North Carolina (Box 10)
      [10-48]
    - Esquire Magazine Symposium (General), 2 folders (Box 10)
      [10-49; 10-50]
- Esquire Magazine Office Files
  The Esquire Magazine Office Files is the largest series in the collection. Arranged alphabetically, this series, although received as part of the Gingrich accession, is more properly the files of the Esquire office. The largest portions of this series pertain to artists and the art department, authors writing for Esquire, personnel, readers' mail, and subject files. The authors files are from the more recent period in Esquire's history, from the mid-1950s to the 1970s. There are files for such individuals as Vance Bourjaily, Howard Fast, Aldous Huxley, Dwight MacDonald, Westbrook Pegler, Allan Seager, and Jesse Stuart.
  - Topical File
    - Advertising, 3 folders (Box 11)
    - Advertisers, A-Z, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Advertisers-General Motors (Box 11)
    - Advertising Agencies
      - A-Z, 4 folders (Box 11)
      - Batten, Barton, Durstine Osborn, Inc. (Box 11)
      - Grey Advertising Agency, Inc. (Box 11)
    - Advertising Complaint s 1962-1971 (Box 11)
    - Advertising-Publisher's letter, 2 folders (Box 11)
    - Advertising-Salesman's letter (Box 11)
    - Agents
      - Estelle Mandel Co. (Box 11)
      - Literary Agents, A-Z (Box 11)
    - Art Department
      - General (Box 11)
      - Artists
        - A-Z (various), 3 folders (Box 11)
        - Gilbert Bundy (Box 11)
        - Chiriaka (Box 11)
        - Alexis de Sakhnoffsky (Box 11)
        - Gobi Uppenberg (Box 11)
        - Peter Helck (Box 11)
        - Syd Hoff (Box 11)
        - Robert J. Lee (Box 11)
        - Dorothy McKay (Box 11)
        - George Petty, 2 folders (Box 11)
        - Barbara Shermund (Box 11)
        - Toune (Box 11)
        - Paul Webb (Box 11)
      - Cartoon index (Box 11)
      - Conde Nast (Adam Magazine) (Box 11)
      - E. Simms Campbell pencil cartoons (Box 11)
    - Authors
      - A, 3 folders (Box 11)
      - B, 3 folders (Box 11)
      - B, 4 folders (Box 12)
      - Vance Bourjaily (Box 12)
      - C, 4 folders (Box 12)
      - D, 4 folders (Box 12)
      - E, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - Paul Engle, 2 folders (Box 12)
      - F, 3 folders (Box 12)
      - Howard Fast (Box 12)
      - George Frazier, 3 folders (Box 12)
      - G, 5 folders (Box 12)
      - Paul Gallico (Box 12)
      - Herb Graffis (Box 12)
      - H, 6 folders (Box 12)
      - Mark Harris (Box 12)
      - Booten Herndon (Box 12)
      - Calvin Hoffman (Box 12)
      - Irving Hoffman, 3 folders (Box 13)
      - Aldous Huxley (Box 13)
      - I-J, 2 folders (Box 13)
      - K-L, 6 folders (Box 13)
      - Meyer Levin (Box 13)
      - Mac-Mc (Box 13)
      - Dwight MacDonald (Box 13)
      - M, 4 folders (Box 13)
      - Martin Mayer (Box 13)
      - Thomas B. Morgan (Box 13)
      - N-0, 2 folders (Box 13)
      - P, 4 folders (Box 13)
      - Dorothy Parker (correspondence about) (Box 13)
      - Westbrook Pegler (Box 13)
      - Q-R, 4 folders (Box 13)
      - Jessyca Russell Gover (Box 13)
      - S, 6 folders (Box 13)
      - Allan Seager, 2 folders (Box 14)
      - George Seldes (Box 14)
      - Peter Stengel (Box 14)
      - Jesse Stuart, 5 folders (Box 14)
      - T-V, 3 folders (Box 14)
      - Roger Treat (Box 14)
      - WXYZ, 4 folders (Box 14)
      - Mary Scott Welch (Box 14)
      - Anthony C. West (Box 14)
      - A.D. Wintle (Box 14)
    - Business Office (Box 14)
    - Circulation Department
      - General (Box 14)
      - Foreign Editions (Box 14)
      - Complaints 1966-1969, 3 folders (Box 14)
      - Subscription promotions, 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Editorial
      - General, 5 folders (Box 14)
      - Automotive (Box 14)
      - Don Erickson (Box 14)
      - Fishing (Box 14)
      - Golf (Box 14)
      - Record 1962-1969 of manuscripts received (Box 14)
      - Silver Anniversary Issue 1958 (Box 14)
      - 35th Anniversary Issue., 2 folders (Box 14)
      - 40th Anniversary Issue (pre-publication material), 2 folders (Box 15)
      - 40th Anniversary Issue (reader response) (Box 15)
      - Arnold Gingrich's page (Box 15)
      - Publisher's page, 5 folders (Box 15)
      - Publisher's page (ideas) (Box 15)
      - "The 43rd New Year" (Box 15)
      - Projects (Box 15)
    - Esquire (size change) (Box 15)
    - Esquire (early "library" or history), 5 folders (Box 15)
    - Fashion Department, 3 folders (Box 15)
    - Fashion Department-Fashion Forum (Box 15)
    - Form letter replies, 4 folders (Box 15)
    - Miscellaneous
      - A, 4 folders (Box 15)
      - Alumni Fun (Box 15)
      - American Society of Magazine Editors (Box 15)
      - Anstey, John (Box 15)
      - Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies 1961-1964 (Box 15)
      - Authors Guild, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - B, 3 folders (Box 15)
      - B, 6 folders (Box 16)
      - Bulletin of Bibliography (Box 16)
      - C, 4 folders (Box 16)
      - D, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - R.R. Donnelley & Sons, Co. (Box 16)
      - E-F, 4 folders (Box 16)
      - Farrar, Straus and Cudahy,Inc. (Box 16)
      - G, 5 folders (Box 16)
      - Geis, Bernard (Box 16)
      - H (T folders) (Box 16)
      - Hirschman, Ira (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 17)
      - I-L, 5 folders (Box 17)
      - M, 5 folders (Box 17)
      - N (Box 17)
      - National Library Week (Box 17)
      - New York Public Library (Box 17)
      - Norris, Hoke (Box 17)
      - O, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Odake, Senmatsu (Box 17)
      - Overseas Press Club (Box 17)
      - P, 3 folders (Box 17)
      - Q-R, 3 folders (Box 17)
      - Rooney, Alicia L (Box 17)
      - Ross, Sue, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - S, 5 folders (Box 17)
      - Saalburg, Leslie, 3 folders (Box 17)
      - Simon & Schuster, Inc. (Box 18)
      - Stevens, Rosalind Blau (Box 18)
      - Streit, Clarence (Box 18)
      - T, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Travel Weekly (Box 18)
      - U (Box 18)
      - V (Box 18)
      - W-Z, 3 folders (Box 18)
      - Wichita Beacon (Box 18)
      - Writer's Digest, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Zenith Sales Corporation-Ted Leitzell., 3 folders (Box 18)
    - Personnel
      - Agencies (Box 18)
      - Applications, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Birmingham, F.A. (Box 18)
      - Blinder, A.L. (Box 18)
      - Former Staff (Box 18)
      - Hayes, Harold, 3 folders (Box 18)
      - Jontry, Jerry, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Smart, David A (Box 18)
      - Smart, John (Box 18)
      - Smart Art Museum (Box 18)
      - Smart Family Foundation (Box 18)
    - Photographers
      - General, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - American Society of Magazine Photographers (Box 18)
    - Production (Box 18)
    - Promotion
      - General, 2 folders (Box 18)
      - Sam Ferber, 3 folders (Box 18)
      - Private and Exhibit Hall Lunches (Box 18)
      - Roundtable lunches, 3 folders (Box 19)
      - Roundtable lunches-Biographies, 2 folders (Box 19)
    - Publicity
      - Miscellaneous clippings, 5 folders (Box 19)
      - New York Herald Tribune.(Sunday), May 24, 1964 (Box 19)
      - Sunday Times (England), January 2, 1966 (Box 19)
      - Detroit Magazine, "Flyrod Man with a Magazine: Michigan's Arnold Gingrich, Esquire," February 20, 1966 (Box 19)
      - Time Magazine July-14,1967 (Box 19)
      - CBC Telescope Program, "Arnold Gingrich, Esquire," January 1968 (Box 19)
      - New York Times, April 25, 1968 (Box 19)
      - Wall Street Journal, May 9, 1968 (Box 19)
      - Chicago Magazine, "Meyer Levin Remembers Esquire," April 1972 (Box 19)
      - New Review, Interview with Arnold Gingrich, Spring, 1973 (Box 19)
      - The Record (Bergen Co., New Jersey), October 4, 1973 (Box 19)
      - New York Times advertisement, "The Buck Must Stop Somewhere, ", December 7, 1973 (Box 19)
      - Business Week advertisement, "This Man Wants Your Company," April 6, 1974 (Box 19)
    - Reader Mail
      - General
        - 1952-1962, 20 folders (Box 19)
        - 1962 re caricatures of Kennedy family (Box 19)
        - 1963-1974, 28 folders (Box 20)
      - Talking Shop and Gifts Department (Box 20)
      - Legal matters, 2 folders (Box 20)
      - Requests and inquiries, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Travel, 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Esquire Publications
    - Reviews of books, 2 folders (Box 20)
    - Armchair Esquire (Box 20)
    - Bedside Esquire (Box 20)
    - Book Projects (Box 20)
    - Esquire-British Edition, 3 folders (Box 20)
    - Cartoon Album (Box 20)
    - Coronet (Box 21)
    - Coronet films (Box 21)
    - Esquire Album of Music for Hosts (Box 21)
    - Esquire Book Club (Box 21)
    - Esquire Cookbook (Box 21)
    - Esquire Club (Box 21)
    - Esquire Etiquette (Box 21)
    - Esquire Book and Drink book (Box 21)
    - Esquire Review (Box 21)
    - Esquire 165
      - Background material (Box 21)
      - Introduction (Box 21)
      - Correspondence (Box 21)
    - Esquire Treasury, 14 folders (Box 21)
    - Fishing book (Box 21)
    - Gentlemen's Quarterly- Apparel Arts (Box 21)
    - Girls from Esquire (Box 21)
    - Guide to Good Grooming (Box 21)
    - Health book (Box 21)
    - Ken Magazine (Box 21)
    - Liquor Intelligencer (Box 21)
    - Magazine projects (Box 21)
    - Television program 1956 (Box 21)
    - Third New Year (Box 21)
- Arnold Gingrich Writing Projects
  The series - Arnold Gingrich Writing Projects - contains drafts of Gingrich's essays, reviews and clippings of some of his writings, and copies of articles that he wrote for Esquire and other magazines. This series also includes copies of books written by Gingrich.
  - Drafts, articles, reviews, clippings, etc.
    - Bibliography of book reviews (Box 21)
    - "Why an Editor" from Nothing But People (Box 21)
    - "A Hundred Masterpieces of the Luthier's Art" (Box 21)
    - "Where did Everybody Go?", 5 folders (Box 21)
    - Introduction to books and book reviews
      - Undated, 2 folders (Box 21)
      - 1943 (Box 21)
      - 1969-1975, 14 folders (Box 21)
    - Notes (Box 22)
    - "Green Count" (Box 22)
    - "Happily Forever After" (1935-1936) (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous magazine articles 1930s (Box 22)
    - Miscellaneous magazine articles 1960s (Box 22)
    - "The Get of the Conqueror", 4 folders (Box 22)
    - "Cast Down the Laurels", 11 folders (Box 22)
    - "Joys Against An Age", 18 folders (Box 22)
    - "Toys of a Lifetime", 5 folders (Box 22)
    - "Thousand Mornings of Music", 4 folders (Box 22)
    - "Nothing But People: The Early Days of Esquire", 9 folders (Box 23)
    - "Business and the Artist, 6 folders (Box 23)
    - "Business in the Arts" Award, 2 folders (Box 23)
    - Ship cruises, 3 folders (Box 23)
    - "The Truth as Private Property" 1966-1967 (Box 23)
  - Books by Arnold Gingrich
    - The Well-Tempered Angler (Box 23)
    - Business & the Arts (Box 23)
    - The Joys of Trout (Box 23)
    - The Fishing in Print (Box 23)
    - Toys of a Lifetime (Box 23)
    - The Gordon Garland (Box 23)
    - A Thousand Mornings of Music (Box 23)
    - American Trout Fishing (Box 23)
- Organizational Affiliations (largely musical and art)
  Organizational Affiliations contains files of materials accumulated and pertaining to Gingrich's participation in business, arts, and other cultural organizations.
  - Affiliate Artists Program (Box 24)
  - American College Theatre Festival (Box 24)
  - American Symphony Orchestra League, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - Arts
    - General, 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Citations (Box 24)
    - Correspondence (Box 24)
  - Arts Advisory Council (Box 24)
  - Associated Councils of the Arts (Box 24)
  - Jockey Club of Paris (Box 24)
  - Lotos Club of New York (Box 24)
  - Business Committee for the Arts., 2 folders (Box 24)
  - National Council on the Arts (Frank Crowther) (Box 24)
  - National Council on the Arts (Nancy Hanks) (Box 24)
  - National Guild of Community Music Schools, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - National Symphony Orchestra Association (Box 24)
  - New Jersey State Council on the Arts (Box 24)
  - New York Board of Trade (Box 24)
  - New York Orchestral Society, Inc. (Box 24)
  - New York State Council on Arts (Box 24)
  - Performance Laboratory, Inc. (Box 24)
  - Riess Alvin (Arts Management) (Box 24)
  - Rockefeller Brothers Fund (Box 24)
  - Smith, George (Box 24)
  - Early concert programs and record catalogs, 3 folders (Box 24)
- Fly-fishing
  The Fly-fishing series concerns Gingrich's participation fly-fishing organization, reviews written of fly-fishing books, and reviews and correspondence received pertaining to his own writings on fly-fishing, most notably The Joys of Trout.
  - Theodore Gordon Flyfishers 1964-1974, 10 folders (Box 24)
  - The Complete Fly Fisherman by John McDonald, 2 folders (Box 24)
  - American Trout Fishing, reviews (Box 24)
  - The Well-Tempered Angler
    - Papers 1963-1966, 6 folders (Box 24)
    - Reviews (Box 24)
  - The Joys of Trout
    - Miscellaneous, 8 folders (Box 24)
    - Letters from readers, 3 folders (Box 24)
  - The Fishing in Print (Box 24)
  - Fishing articles by A.G. (Box 24)
- Sound recordings
  Sound Recordings is a series of reel-to-reel audio-tapes of radio programs and seminars in which Gingrich participated. The topic of one of these was "The Moral Responsibilities of the Press." Compact discs have been made of these recordings.
  - Mutual Broadcasting System Network June 17, 1967 (Box 25)
  - Celebrity's choice with Dick Hubert, WABC-FM September 25, 1966 (Box 25)
  - NBC Radio Monitor January 20, 1964 (Box 25)
  - National Council of the Episcopal Church radio program circa 1963 (Box 25)
  - "Moral Responsibilities of the Press" Institute Francois de Presse of the University of Paris April 24, 1959 (Box 25)
- Photographs
  The Visual Materials series consists of ten envelopes of photographs of Gingrich, alone and as part of larger groups, receiving awards, and with his family and friends; also one envelope of violin photographs. There are three DVDs of various television appearances of Gingrich.
  - Photographs
    - "Alumni Fun" broadcast January 23, 1966 (Box 25)
    - Awards given and received (Box 25)
    - Business in the arts (Box 25)
    - Detroit boat race 1949 (Box 25)
    - Family, homes, car (Box 25)
    - Friends (Box 25)
    - Oklahoma Library Association conference 1969 (Box 25)
    - Gingrich and others (Box 25)
    - A Thousand Mornings of Music (Box 25)
    - Violin (Box 25)
    - Esquire Magazine cover art (Back to College), 5x7 negative (Box 25)
  - DVDs
    - AG television appearance on Conversation program WILL TV, host Bill Dale May 13, 1964 (Box 25)
    - CBC Telescope program (Box 25)
Related Material
The records of Esquire Magazine are also held by the Bentley Library and should be used in conjunction with the Gingrich papers.